<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-sfc-oam-packet-02" ipr="trust200902"
     updates="8300">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="SFC OAM Packet">OAM Packet and Behavior in the Network
    Service Header (NSH)</title>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>sfc</workgroup>

    <keyword>Diagnostic</keyword>

    <keyword>Troubelshooting</keyword>

    <keyword>Service Function Chaining</keyword>

    <keyword>Automation</keyword>

    <keyword>SDN</keyword>

    <keyword>Programmable Networks</keyword>

    <keyword>Service Differentiation</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document clarifies an ambiguity in the Network Service Header
      (NSH) specification related to the handling of O bit. In particular,
      this document clarifies the meaning of "OAM packet".</t>

      <t>This document updates RFC 8300.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>This document clarifies an ambiguity related to the definition of
      Operations, Administration, and Maintenance (OAM) packet discussed in
      <xref target="RFC8300"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The processing of the O bit in the Network Service Header (NSH) must
      follow the updated behavior specified in <xref
      target="anupdate"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>This document makes use of the terms defined in <xref
      target="RFC7665"></xref> and <xref target="RFC8300"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The document defines the following terms:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="SFC data plane element:">refers to SFC-aware Service
          Function (SF), Service Function Forwarder (SFF), SFC Proxy, or
          Classifier as defined in the SFC data plane architecture <xref
          target="RFC7665"></xref> and further refined in <xref
          target="RFC8300"></xref>.</t>

          <t hangText="OAM control element:">an NSH-aware element that is
          capable of generating NSH OAM packets. An SFC data plane element may
          behave as an OAM control element.</t>

          <t hangText="SFC OAM data:">refers to an OAM request (e.g.,
          Connectivity Verification and Continuity Checks <xref
          target="RFC7276"></xref>), any data that influences how to execute a
          companion OAM request (e.g., identity of a terminating SF), the
          output data of an OAM request, and any combination thereof.</t>

          <t hangText="User data:">refers to user packets cited in Section 5.7
          of <xref target="RFC7665"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="anupdate" title="An Update to RFC8300">
      <t>This document updates Section 2.2 of <xref target="RFC8300"></xref>
      as follows:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="OLD: "><vspace blankLines="1" /><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="O bit:">Setting this bit indicates an OAM packet
              (see [RFC6291]). The actual format and processing of SFC OAM
              packets is outside the scope of this specification (for example,
              see [SFC-OAM-FRAMEWORK] for one approach).<vspace
              blankLines="1" />The O bit MUST be set for OAM packets and MUST
              NOT be set for non-OAM packets. The O bit MUST NOT be modified
              along the SFP.<vspace blankLines="1" />SF/SFF/SFC
              Proxy/Classifier implementations that do not support SFC OAM
              procedures SHOULD discard packets with O bit set, but MAY
              support a configurable parameter to enable forwarding received
              SFC OAM packets unmodified to the next element in the chain.
              Forwarding OAM packets unmodified by SFC elements that do not
              support SFC OAM procedures may be acceptable for a subset of OAM
              functions, but it can result in unexpected outcomes for others;
              thus, it is recommended to analyze the impact of forwarding an
              OAM packet for all OAM functions prior to enabling this
              behavior. The configurable parameter MUST be disabled by
              default.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="NEW: "><vspace blankLines="1" /><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="O bit:">Setting this bit indicates an NSH OAM
              packet. Such a packet is any NSH-encapsulated packet that
              exclusively includes SFC OAM data. SFC OAM data can be included
              in the Fixed-Length Context Header, optional Context Headers,
              and/or the inner packet. <vspace blankLines="1" />The O bit is
              typically set by an OAM controller or a final destination of an
              NSH OAM packet that triggers a response (e.g., a specific
              SFC-aware SF, the last SFF of an SFP). <vspace
              blankLines="1" />The O bit MUST be set for NSH OAM packets and
              MUST NOT be set for non-OAM packets. The O bit MUST NOT be
              modified along the SFP.<vspace blankLines="1" />NSH-encapsulated
              packets that include user data are not considered as NSH OAM
              packets even if some SFC OAM data (e.g., record route) is also
              supplied in the packet. <vspace blankLines="1" />When SFC OAM
              data is included in the inner packet, the Next Protocol field is
              set to reflect the structure of that inner OAM packet. The
              setting and processing of the O bit neither assumes nor expects
              detailed analysis of the content of any inner IP packet carried
              by the NSH. As such, SFFs, SFC-aware SFs, and SFC Proxies SHOULD
              discard any NSH packets with the O bit set and Next Protocol set
              to something that is not itself an OAM protocol. This includes
              discarding the packet when the O bit is set and the Next
              Protocol is set to 0x01 (IPv4), 0x02 (IPv6), 0x03 (MPLS), or
              0x05 (Ethernet). This is meant to prevent non deterministic
              behaviors, e.g., at SFs that receive such packets. SFC data
              plane elements MAY support a configuration parameter to filter
              valid Next Protocol values in NSH OAM packets. <vspace
              blankLines="1" />An NSH OAM packet MAY include optional Context
              Headers (e.g., a subscriber identifier <xref
              target="RFC8979"></xref> or a flow identifier <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-sfc-nsh-tlv"></xref>) that are used to
              influence the processing of the packet by SFC data plane
              elements. <vspace blankLines="1" />An NSH OAM packet MAY include
              SFC OAM data in both Context Headers and the inner packet. The
              processing (including the order) of the SFC OAM data SHOULD be
              specified in the relevant OAM or Context Header specification.
              <vspace blankLines="1" />SFC-aware SF/SFF/SFC Proxy/Classifier
              implementations that do not support SFC OAM procedures SHOULD
              discard packets with O bit set, but MAY support a configurable
              parameter to enable forwarding received NSH OAM packets
              unmodified to the next element in the chain. Forwarding NSH OAM
              packets unmodified by SFC data plane elements that do not
              support SFC OAM procedures may be acceptable for a subset of OAM
              functions, but it can result in unexpected outcomes for others;
              thus, it is recommended to analyze the impact of forwarding an
              NSH OAM packet for all OAM functions prior to enabling this
              behavior. The configurable parameter MUST be disabled by
              default. <vspace blankLines="1" />The actual format and
              additional processing of NSH OAM packets is outside the scope of
              this specification.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not make any request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Data plane SFC-related security considerations, including privacy,
      are discussed in Section 6 of <xref target="RFC7665"></xref> and Section
      8 of <xref target="RFC8300"></xref>. Additional security considerations
      related to SFC OAM are discussed in Section 9 of <xref
      target="RFC8924"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Any data included in an NSH OAM packet SHOULD be integrity-protected
      <xref target="RFC9145"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>Thanks to Jim Guichard, Greg Mirsky, Joel Halpern, Christian
      Jacquenet, Dirk von-Hugo, Carlos Pignataro, and Frank Brockners for the
      comments.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Barry Leiba for the art directorate review and Russ Housley
      for the security directorate review. </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8300'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9145'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7665'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8979'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-sfc-nsh-tlv'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8924'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7276'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6291'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
